<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A iournall, or briefe report of the late seruice in Britaigne, by the Prince de Dombes generall of the French Kings army in those partes assisted with her Maiesties forces at this present there, vnder the conduct of Sir Iohn Norreis: aduertised by letters from the said prince to the Kings ambassadour here resident with her Maiesty, and confirmed by like aduertisements from others, imployed in that seruice. Published, to aunswere the slanderous bruites raised of late by some euill affected to that and other good actions, vndertaken against the enemy of Gods true religion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839714</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 322:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A iournall, or briefe report of the late seruice in Britaigne, by the Prince de Dombes generall of the French Kings army in those partes assisted with her Maiesties forces at this present there, vnder the conduct of Sir Iohn Norreis: aduertised by letters from the said prince to the Kings ambassadour here resident with her Maiesty, and confirmed by like aduertisements from others, imployed in that seruice. Published, to aunswere the slanderous bruites raised of late by some euill affected to that and other good actions, vndertaken against the enemy of Gods true religion.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn VVolfe, and are to be sold at his shop right ouer against the great south-doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Apparently a continuation of "Newes sent out of Britayn, and other places on the third of June 1591. to a gentleman of account" (STC 18654.3).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norris, John, --  Sir, 1547?-1597.</term>
               <term>Montpensier, Henri de Bourbon, --  duc du, 1573-1608.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Guingamp (France) --  History --  Siege, 1591 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4161:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4161:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <p>A IOVRNALL, OR Briefe report of the late ſeruice in Britaigne, by the <hi>Prince</hi> de Dombes Generall of the French Kings Army in thoſe partes, aſſiſted with her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties forces at this preſent there, vnder the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Sir Iohn Norreis: aduertiſed by letters from the ſaid <hi>Prince</hi> to the Kings Ambaſſadour here reſident with her Maieſty, and confirmed by like aduertiſements from others, imployed in that ſeruice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed, to aunſwere the ſlanderous bruites raiſed of late by ſome euill affected to that and other good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, vndertaken againſt the enemy of Gods true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn VVolfe, and are to be ſold at his ſhop right ouer againſt the great South-doore of Paules. 1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4161:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4161:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the winning of the Towne of <hi>Guingcamp,</hi> the purpoſe of the Prince was, to haue aſſailed the Towne of <hi>Morlaix,</hi> to the ende to haue reduced the ſayd Town, and the reſt of <hi>Baſſe-Britagne</hi> to the Kings obedience: howbeit vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the D. of <hi>Mercoeur</hi> was remoued from <hi>Pontiuy,</hi> where he ioyned with 4000. Spaniards, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the leading of <hi>Don Iuan de Lagula</hi> and was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching towards <hi>Morlaix,</hi> by the way of <hi>Corlay:</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> therevppon diſcouering the forces of the ſaide Duke, which were of ſeauen hundred horſe, foure thouſand Spaniards, and two thouſand Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuſiers French: conſidered how dangerous it might be to ingage his Army before a towne, vntill he were Maiſter of the fielde, the enemy being of more ſtrength then he, and in a countrey of aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and where he might bee aſſiſted with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of peiſants, long before armed and reſolued for the enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4161:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->Vpon theſe difficulties, the <hi>Prince</hi> made ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Towne of <hi>Guingcamp,</hi> aſwell to amend the fortifications, as to repaire the breach made by hys Canon, (the better to aſſure the Towne from the enemy) as to attend the bringing of two Canons, &amp; two Culuerings, drawne from <hi>Breſt</hi> to <hi>Lagnon,</hi> with certayne powder, bullets, and other munition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayed out of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Pinpaoul,</hi> to the end that the ſame being in place of aſſurance, the enemy might not take occaſion to driue the Prince from his other enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth of Iune, the D. de <hi>Mercoeur</hi> arriued at <hi>Corlay,</hi> within three leagues of <hi>Guingcamp,</hi> a caſtle pretending to hold for the king, but in the poſſeſſion of <hi>Madame de Guymenay,</hi> whoſe brother, <hi>Monſieur de Boydolphin</hi> is Lieutenant to the D. <hi>de Mercoeur,</hi> ſo that it ſeemed the partie was made before hand, for that the next day after they did arriue, the caſtle rendred without ſeeing the Canon, and the Captain remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the enemy: &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place the Duke ſent to the Prince a Trompeter about certaine priſoners of ours, taken at <hi>Corlay,</hi> who ſignifyed to the ſayd <hi>Prince</hi> that he had in charge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the D. to entreat him to appoint ſom day &amp; place of battel: wherunto the <hi>Prince</hi> made anſwere, that it was the moſt acceptable newes that could be brought vnto him, and a thing which he had often ſought and deſired, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto at this time, he hoped to enforce the ſaid Duke to whom he would not return anſwer by the mouth of a Trompeter, which might be diſaduowed, but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4161:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->
by a writing ſigned with his owne hand, which was accordingly performed as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Prince <hi>de Dombes</hi> Gouernour for the King in <hi>Daulphine,</hi> and Generall of his army in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Britaigne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VPPon a meſſage deliuered to the ſayd Prince by a Trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter ſent to him from the Duke of <hi>Mercoeur,</hi> for other cauſes, by the which hee was ſollicited to aſſigne and make choiſe of ſome day &amp; place of battaile, deſired by the Duke: he conſidering how ſpeaches of that nature deliuered by a Trompeter, might be diſadvowed, and deſiring as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſithence his firſt comming into that Countrey, that ſome like occaſion might be offered whereby the miſeries and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamites of the ſame might haue an end, which he had made appeare by effects, thought meet for the better aduancing of ſo good a worke, by this writing ſigned with his hand, and ſent by a Trompeter of his owne, to ſignify to the ſayd D. <hi>de Mercoeur,</hi> that the thing he moſt deſired, was to come to the iſſue of ſo happie a day, and therfore would yeeld to him the choyſe of the day and place for that encounter, ſo that the place of meeting might be capable to receiue the two armies in order of Battaile, and to auoyd the delayes that might growe by want of reſolution herein, he thought the <hi>Lawne</hi> of <hi>Menay</hi> very fitte for this purpoſe, concluding, that if this honorable reſolution ſhould chance to be differred vpon any alteration whatſoeuer on either part: he the ſaid Prince doth proteſt before God and the world, that the honour and reputation of him that ſhall herein make default, ſhall incur
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4161:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
the ſtaine and preiudice that ſhall grow thereof.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at the Campe before <hi>Guingcamp,</hi> 
                        <date>the ſeuenth of Iune. 1591.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The 8. of Iune the Duke of <hi>Mercoeur</hi> remooued from <hi>Corlay</hi> to Saint <hi>Gilles,</hi> two ſmall leagues diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Chaſteau-Laudran:</hi> The ſame day alſo the Prince departed from <hi>Guingcamp,</hi> about three of the clocke in the morning, and lodged that night at <hi>Chaſteau-Laudran,</hi> where his own Trumpeter with the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter of the Duke de <hi>Mercoeur</hi> met him, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an anſwere from the ſaid Duke ſigned with his hand, the contents whereof followe.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>The Duke de <hi>Mercoeur</hi> and of <hi>Penthieure</hi> Peere of <hi>France,</hi> Prince of the Holy Empire, Lorde of <hi>Martigues</hi> and Gouernour of <hi>Britaine.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAuing peruſed the writing of the Prince <hi>de Dombes,</hi> ſent, vpon the challenge of battel, deliuered by his trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter: euen as he hath many times ſought the occaſion, and deſiring nothing more, then by a battel to free this Prouince from the miſeries wherwith it hath bin ouerwhelmed, by the repaire of the ſaid Prince into the ſame, and to withſtand the apparant ruine thereof like to enſue, by the domination of an hereticall king, with the ouerthrow of our holy Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: for the deſire he hath to ſee the iſſue of ſo happy a day, and becauſe the day and place is referred to his election, is reſolued to be ready with his army on Thorſeday next at ten of the clocke in the morning, in the fitteſt place for ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4161:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->
betweene <hi>Corlay</hi> and <hi>Guingcamp,</hi> and to come on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the beſt part of the way: which ought not to be refuſed or diferred in ſeeking of any place more remote or vnfit with out diſhonour: the ſaid Duke proteſting before God (from whom as fighting in his cauſe he hopeth of victorie) that he neuer had other intent, and that if the ſaide Prince ſhal ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refuſe or diferre this offer, he ſhal ſhew to the world, that his actions are not anſwerable to his bragges, and ſhal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by blemiſh his honour and reputation.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at the Campe at <hi>Corlay</hi> 
                        <date>the 8. of Iune 1591.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hereunto the Prince for many good reſons, gaue ſuch reply as the Duke might perceiue, hee woulde not contende with him onely in tearmes, but to giue him all the prouocation that poſſible hee might to come to handes returned him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>The Prince <hi>de Dombes</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Daulphine,</hi> Lieutenant Generall for the King in his armie in <hi>Britaigne.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAuing ſeene the anſwere of Duke <hi>Mercoeur</hi> of the eight of this moneth ſigned with his hand, vpon the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer made of the day and place of battel to be giuen, ſaith, he was ſent into this prouince to chaſtice and puniſh thoſe that are traiterouſly rebelled againſt the King, of whome the ſaide Duke being chiefe, doth manifeſt how he ſhunneth and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the preſence of the ſaid Prince, and the paine and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of his rebellion: and in regard of the lewd imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4161:5"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
giuen by his anſwer to the King, &amp; to the ſaid Prince, he ſaith he lyeth, and ſhal lie as often as he ſhall ſo ſay.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>At the Campe at <hi>Chaſteau-Laudran</hi> 
                        <date>the ninth of Iune. 1591.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <argument>
                     <p>This Cartel was ſent by a trumpeter, and deliuered to the Duke in the preſence of many of the principal men of his army.</p>
                  </argument>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THe Duke greatly moued with this Cartell, did openly by a ſolemne othe vowe, within 3. daies to offer battaile to the <hi>Prince,</hi> and on the 9. of Iune being wenſday, diſlodged, &amp; that day incamped at <hi>Quelenec</hi> a Village about a league and a halfe from <hi>Chaſteau-Laudran,</hi> ſcituate at the foote of a high hill, which by deepe hedges, ditches and incloſures, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted a little heath of two miles compas, to which Heath vpon the diſcouery of the approach of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy by our army, the <hi>Prince</hi> mounteth on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, and goeth to diſcerne and make choiſe of the place for the battaile betweene the ennemy and him, and findeth about three quarters of a league of the Village aforeſaide, a large plaine or Heath, skirted in the ſide of the ennemie with a Coppice, a litle hill, &amp; the ground raiſed with ditches of great aduantage for the enemie, who by three large paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges might without any difficulty, enter into the ſaid Heath.</p>
            <p>The tenth day of Iune, the ennemy, within one quarter of a league of the Heath, ſheweth his whole army in order of battaile vpon the top of a hill: the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4161:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
               <hi>Prince</hi> on the other ſide put his troups in ordonance within the Heath, diſpoſing the ſame by the aduiſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Norreis</hi> into three Battallions, whereof the infanterie Engliſh made two, &amp; the Lancekneights the third. This day was ſpent with ſome light skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, entertained by our men, and followed euen to the maine of the enemies army.</p>
            <p>The 11. of Iune being Friday, the enemy drew his army to the foot of the hill, and placed his artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vpon the ſide of the Heath, in a place of ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, as it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded in the nature of a Cauallier all the whole Heath, where he poſſeſſed the ground neare about him, &amp; bordred al the hedges with ſhot: and by the time that this was perfourmed our army was marched into the Heath in order of battaile, and preſently ſent out two hundred footemen to viewe the countenance of the ennemy, who aduauncing themſelues, charged the ennemy, draue them to their ſtrengths, put them from their hedges and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricades, and ſlewe diuerſe of them. Vpon the retrait of theſe two hundred men, the Duke put forth fiue hundred French, and three hundred Spaniardes to repoſſeſſe the places, whom he followed with the great of his arme. Which perceiued by the <hi>Prince,</hi> remaining on the Heath with <hi>Monſieur</hi> de la <hi>Hunaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye</hi> commanding the auantgard, and hauing his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of horſe in battaile on the right hand of the white Cornet, and General <hi>Norreis</hi> (who in this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gaue good proofe of his wiſedome and valour) Monſieur de <hi>Pogny,</hi> de <hi>Pruneaux,</hi> de <hi>Monmartin,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4161:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
de <hi>Baſtenay,</hi> order was giuen for the putting foorth of three hundred footemen, commanded by Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Anthony Wingfield</hi> Sergeant maior, and captaine <hi>Morton,</hi> and the Engliſh horſe lead by Captaine <hi>Anthony Sherley,</hi> and the skirmiſh hotely proſecuted, the enemy let ſlippe a great number of ſhotte vnder the defence of the hedges, thinking to lodge them on the left hand, &amp; to haue taken ſome two or three houſes, &amp; a ſmall wood vpon the edge of the Heath. The <hi>Prince</hi> commaunded to be drawen out of the Battallion of the Lancekneights one hundred men, ſhotte and pikes, and one hundred and fiftie ſhotte French, lead by the Baron de <hi>Molac,</hi> backed with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty light horſe, conducted by Monſieur de la <hi>Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaye,</hi> appointed to force the enemy from the place they had taken.</p>
            <p>This direction was valiantly proſecuted by ours, but ſpecially by the Engliſh, ſo as the enimies horſe and footemen which were in the plaine were forced to flie, many ſlaine, and the reſt driuen to ſaue them ſelues wythin their Artillerie, where the whole ſtrength of Spaniardes, with the reſt of their armie was placed. There was taken in this charge Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de <hi>Guebrian</hi> Colonell of the footemen of the ennemy by Monſieur de la <hi>Tremblay,</hi> and ſlaine <hi>Don Roderigo,</hi> chiefe Mareſchall of the Spaniards, a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Captaine, and to the number of two hundred French, and three ſcore Spaniards.</p>
            <p>This reſolute charge ſo amazed the army of the enemy, that our men were ſuffered within tenne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4161:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
of their Cannon to diſarme the dead, lead away priſoners, and retired at their eaſe, the enemy neuer proffering to followe.</p>
            <p>In this charge Captaine <hi>Anthony Sherley</hi> gaue ſuch an example to the French horſe, as was admired and much commended in al the army, and the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on foote perfourmed their partes with no leſſe valour and reputation, namely, the Sergeant Maior, Captaine <hi>Dolphin,</hi> and Lieutenant <hi>Long,</hi> who beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued himſelfe moſt valiantly, and receiued in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fiue harquebuz ſhotte: but all ſuch as by Gods helpe within fewe dayes he will be able to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the field.</p>
            <p>The reſidue of the day wherein this charge was giuen, was ſpent in ſlight skirmiſhes and canonades.</p>
            <p>The twelfth of Iune, the enemy made a very great ſhewe to come foorth to the battaile, but at the laſt, ſent out ſome number of ſhotte to the skirmiſh, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom captaine <hi>Anthony Sherley</hi> with fifteen horſe and a fewe foote, made head, and put them ſpeedily to their heeles, purſuing them to their Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricades, where his horſe was ſhotte in the head, and Maiſter <hi>Kempe</hi> a Gentleman of that Cornet ſlaine, and Maiſter <hi>Charles Blunt</hi> his horſe killed vnder him with the Canon, and himſelfe ſomewhat wounded.</p>
            <p>The thirteenth of Iune, the ennemy alſo offered ſome light skirmiſhes, but woulde not abide anie charge either of horſe or foote.</p>
            <p>On Monday the 14. of Iune we expected the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, as vndertaken by <hi>Don Iuan de Lagula</hi> General
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4161:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
of the Spaniards, in the honor of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> whoſe day it was with them, but nothing was done: and that day ſeemed to ende their choler, for that the Duke did prepare the ſame night to diſlodge, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing his Cannons from the place where they were planted, and the day following repaſſed the hil where he firſt appeared, and from thence retired to <hi>Quelenec,</hi> where yet he remaineth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prince</hi> hereuppon after he had continued his army on the Heath, from Friday the eleauenth of Iune, till the fifteenth of the ſame, alwayes in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to haue giuen battaile (the weather hauing bin for the moſt part exceeding wet) withdrew his artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie, diſlodged his army, and returned euery troupe to the ſeuerall quarters, where they had before lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, expecting the intention of the enemy, thereby to aduiſe of the meanes to attempt vpon him.</p>
            <p>The two armies continued encamped the one neere to the other by the ſpace of ſixe dayes, in all which time the enimy neuer durſt preſume to draw his army into the Heath, nor make choiſe of ground for battaile, notwithſtanding the brauery of his chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday the ſixteenth day of Iune, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de la <hi>Nouë</hi> with the troupe of the Conte <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery</hi> being an hundred Curates, and the Conte de <hi>Combourg</hi> came vnto <hi>Chaſteau-Laudran,</hi> whoſe arriuall giueth hope of good ſucceſſe in the Kinges affaires, to the ruine and confuſion of his enemies.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4161:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
                  <head>The <hi>Prince</hi> de <hi>Dombes</hi> in a particular Letter of the twentith of Iune, ſent to the Kings Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour heere reſident with her Maieſty gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this teſtimony of the valour of our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and Nation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Send this briefe diſcourſe of the late action, wherewith you may acquaint her Maieſtie, proteſting truely vnto you, that I obſerue daily more and more the valour and woorth of Generall <hi>Norreis,</hi> who hath ſo worthely carried himſelfe in all theſe actions, that he hath wonne greate honour and reputation here, and ſo haue all the Captaines and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours of that Nation vnder his conduct: and if the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes had had courage and valour like to theſe Engliſh troupes which it hath pleaſed her Maieſtie to ſend vnto vs, we had made an ende of the miſeries of this Prouince, by the happy iſſue of a battaile.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And Monſieur de la <hi>Nouë</hi> in a Letter of the 21. of Iune to the ſaide Embaſſadour, yeeldeth his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the actions, and of the General and our Nation in theſe termes:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THe enemy was retired two leagues from our Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my arriuall, and is ſithence gon further off: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue mee there was made a braue attempt vppon him,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4161:8"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
as Generall <hi>Norreis</hi> can beſt ſignifie vnto you, who was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at all that was offered. Our determination is ſtill to draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Battail, which can not at al times at our choiſe bee effected, as well by reaſon of the qualtiy of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as that the Duke of <hi>Mercoeur</hi> will commit nothing to hazarde. Without the ſuccour ſent hither by the Queene of England, Brittaigne had beene greatly in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, (I meane ſo much thereof as is poſseſſed by the King) who in that reſpect is greatly bound vnto her Maieſty. It is a verie faire and gallant troupe of men, and are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a moſt braue Captain Generall <hi>Norreis,</hi> a man very tractable, and with whom we are well fitted in diſpoſition.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4161:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
